Hello everybody.
Here is Tatiana Bazzichelli,
the director of the Disruption Network Club,
and I'm very happy to welcome all of you in Berlin
and also welcome the people that are following us online.
This event is very important for us
because it's our 25th conference
and we are also launching our book,
Whistleblowing for Change.
The idea of these events was to collect
contributes from 30 speakers of the past
of the Disruption Network Club
and try to reflect on the impact of whistleblowing
on culture, politics, and society.
And also thanks to the people that wrote in the book,
we got to know new people that also decided
to write for us on the book
and the panel that I'm going to introduce now
is actually a combination of some of our past speakers
and also new, very important people
that we got to know thanks to our network of trust.
And so first I wanted to thank the audience here in Berlin
and also the audience online
and the reminder that we have a chat.
So if they want to ask questions after
and during our introduction
and during the panel that they are welcome to do
and after the conversation we will then get your questions
so we can also bring them directly to the speakers.
Just to give a bit of a context
of what we are doing here,
we just watched the German premiere
of the film United States Versus Reality Winner.
It's a film that was directed by Sonja Kennebeck
that we also have on stage with us
and it's a film about the NSA contractor Reality Winner
who disclosed a document
about Russian election interference to the media.
Winner was arrested on June 3rd, 2017
and really this week she started a new phase at home
and I have to say that we know
that she is also not completely free
because there are a lot of restrictions on her
and we are going to learn also more
about the situation during this panel.
But first I really wanted to thank Reality Winner
and Winner Davies for being with us this night
and I have to say it's really, really an honor for us
and I'm also so touched to see them at the distance
of course would have been wonderful to have them with us
but it's so great.
And I have to say Reality and Billy
you really deserve this big applause
because here in Berlin everybody was really waiting
for these moments for many years actually
and I don't know, I'm so touched also personally
that I'm getting a bit emotional
because it's also really a big moment
for the Disruption Network Club
and so we just watched the film about your story
and I'm sure that many people have questions.
Also I also want to really deeply thanks Billy
for the relationship we had in the past months
to write the book Contribution
that she also has on the book.
So I really want to tell everybody read this
because it's a wonderful story
from the perspective of a mother
that also is fighting for justice
and the right of her daughter.
So thank you Billy and also thank you Reality.
I'm so happy to have you with us
and also want to welcome our speakers
and our moderator.
First I start with John Kiriakou
that then will be introduced probably by Anna
but I want to say that John Kiriakou
was already with us in 2017
and in that specific event
we were also celebrating the release of Chelsea Manning.
So actually today we were discussing
now you are back with us
and we are celebrating also the release of Reality Winner.
So I mean these are very important moments
and it's really wonderful to have you back with us
and I already introduced before Sonia
but Anna will do it again
and I want to introduce Anna Myers
that is going to moderate this panel.
So Anna Myers is the Executive Director
of the Whistleblowing International Network.
She has worked in the field of whistleblowing for 20 years
advising individual whistleblowers, employers
of all sides and sector
and national international policy makers.
Anna is originally from Canada
and was Deputy Director of Public Concern Network
for nine years now is called Protect
and has worked at Group of States Against Corruption
and at the Government Accountability Project
in Washington DC.
So now I leave to you Anna, the conversation
and also then let's remind to call in
also the audience online.
Thank you.
Thank you so much Tassiana.
Well, it's such an honor to be here with all of you
and I think the one joy, well a private joy of mine
of being moderator is I get to ask questions first
and I'm so delighted to welcome Billy
and Reality to this event.
We're sitting in a really lovely room
in the middle of Berlin
and it's in a gorgeous building
and we've got these kind of high ceilings
so there's a kind of echo here.
So the applause for you was quite astounding
and was amplified very much though.
I wanted to let the audience know
and those who are just joining us
that Reality has finished her prison term this week
but she's still under some orders
and so there will be some limits
to what the questions are that people can ask her
or that she's allowed to talk about.
Both Billy and Reality will let us know
when we've crossed those lines
but she basically cannot talk at all
about the classified information
and really about the case
but she can talk about her interests
and she'll let us know what she feels like speaking
if she would like to speak to us
and I will introduce briefly our panelists
because they can introduce themselves
so much better than I can.
We have Sonia, who's Kennebec
who's the documentary director of this film.
She has a long history of working
in the doing documentaries
and working in investigative journalism
and it really struck me
as I was watching the documentary
and a question I would have is
is it really a longer piece of investigative journalism
or is it an entire different beast really?
Because certainly what we all felt
as we watched this documentary today
or at least I can speak for myself
is the layers that you were able to weave in
of the personal stories,
the context in which this case
happened and also all the issues
that were raised around justice
and whistleblowers and how it works in practice
so we really had a full picture
and it raises I'm sure everybody has a lot of questions
and Sonia has done this work for a long time
and has really started to focus on whistleblowers
I think in the last three documentary films
that she's done in particular
and I'd really like to understand a little bit more
about why you started to become interested in this
and why you chose reality
after focusing on the drone program
and the whistleblowers there with National Bird
and with the hacking situation in the family
with public enemy or enemy of the state
so there's a lot to ask you there
John it's great to meet you again
and John you heard him in the film
very articulate about both the issues
that are raised by reality's case
but obviously has lived through the experience himself
as a former CIA employee
he's an illustrious career as well
and what really comes out from both his story
and reality story is you were hard workers
you did your jobs, you served your countries
and you were very dedicated to what you did
and then there was a point at which you felt
you needed to speak up
and there's a lot that happened after that
Billy you are both a mother and now an activist
an advocate you really were thrown into this
by being in a family of people
that were clearly dedicated
and I'd really like to ask both Billy and reality
if they'd like to start by perhaps making a statement
about your thoughts and feelings now
and what you've been dealing with recently
to the audience
and we'll let everyone have an opportunity
to make that statement to the audience
and then I'll ask a few questions
and then we'll open it up
so which one of you would like to start?
Billy would you like to start
or would reality like to say something?
Sure I'll go ahead and start
I want to say how grateful I am
that you all included us in this event
it was such an honor to be asked to contribute to the book
I've never been asked to contribute to a book
I've never been published
and so that was a challenge
and it was such an honor for me
and then this event here
this whistleblowing event
I was also very happy to see
that you guys were able to incorporate the documentary
United States versus reality winner into your program
and I'm happy that the audience there
and the people who are online
were able to actually see the documentary
to see what's happened in reality's case
to see the persecution of her by our government
what happened to her
just because she did the right thing
she released information to the American people
that she felt that we needed at a time
when we desperately needed it
and you know the reaction
of the United States government against her
is a story that really needs to be out there
needs to be told
I know as you said
I was not an activist before this
I still don't consider myself an activist
I still consider myself a mother
I consider myself a mother
who will continue to fight
until I see that justice is done for my daughter
we continue to fight and ask for either clemency
for her sentence to end
or for a full pardon
so that she can be completely and totally free
at some point
to tell her side of this story
when I started this work
as far as being her voice
that's really what it was meant to be
because our government locked her up
and they silenced reality
and somebody needed to be her voice
somebody needed to tell her side and her story
and that's you know what I set out to do
I had so much help along the way
Sonia was a huge help in doing the documentary
there's also other people that helped me
and supported me along the way
and also supported reality through this
and I'm so very grateful for every single person
who has helped us
and you know gave me the strength
so that I didn't stop
the standing ovation that we received
when this started just kind of blew me away
because that was something I really wasn't expecting
I really am grateful to everyone there for that
Well, much, much deserved
and we're delighted you could be here
Reality, is there anything you'd like to say at this point?
I'm sure there will be answers
about my actual status later on
going forward in the restrictions
but for right now I just wanna say thank you
it's a surprise if I even find people in my own country
that care about my story
let alone all you find people in Berlin
so feeling the love from across the Atlantic
is really, really nice
it's really appreciated
and hi, Sonia
So for those of you who may have just joined us online
we've just watched this incredible documentary
about a young woman who was arrested
and then charged under the Espionage Act in the US
she was charged with releasing to the media
a single document that actually showed
and was about Russian interference in the 2016 elections
this was at a time as all of us will recall
doesn't seem very long ago at all
where we were from afar watching the elections in the US
and Donald Trump was elected
and one of the things that really comes out
in the documentary is the context
in which the prosecution was taking place
and the fact that
and there's lots of issues around how she was treated
by those who were arresting her and her rights
and then of course the courtroom setting
and the Espionage Act is something
I hope John will give us a little run through on
but it's a very draconian law
and it is not fit for what it's being used for
and it gives people no chance for a defense
and it's one of the ones that is really
where the whistle-blowing issue is starkly in play
because you're talking about classification,
national security, the state
and you're talking about the public's right
to know in the public interest
and we have this discussion that
or actually I would say a kind of argument
that often ensues where people are called traitors or heroes
and most of us need to think
in a much more nuanced way about this
and the question that I tend to ask myself
is did I want to know
and if it's a yes I did
well then why didn't other people tell us
and if we need whistle-blowers
why do we need them it's a big question
and we should be celebrating them
if we can't get the information any other way.
Sonja, you've been going down this road now for a while
and I know that you worked in Berlin for many years
and your roots are international
but German and now you're in New York as well.
It was a question I had.
You know, is there a big difference
in making a documentary
than doing an investigative reporter?
Is it longer investigations
and would you like to explain how you got
what made you choose this story
and how you got here?
So, you know, because we as a team
we've been focusing on whistle-blower stories
it's really wonderful to have the German Premier
at the whistle-blowering for a change conference.
With an audience that understands
what whistle-blowering means
and people, many of you I know
who are advocating for a wider public
to understand what whistle-blowering means
which is exposing ways fraud, abuse,
government misconduct in the public interest
and I think more people have to know that
and I think everyone here
has been doing incredible educational work.
It is very emotional for me to see this film
with an audience but also, you know,
in the film we are documenting the four years
that reality was spending imprisoned
and to see reality next to Billy
free right now in the house
or almost, you know, hopefully,
hopefully someday really free
but closer to freedom is really, really wonderful
and I can actually see it in the eyes
of my team members who are here right now,
Torsten Lapp, the director of photography
and Maxine Gurdike, the editor
that, you know, they are really moved as well
and yeah, I actually want to start by thanking reality.
Reality, thank you for your courage
but also your trust in us
when you were in a really vulnerable position
and probably, you know, everyone would have understood
if you didn't have any trust in journalists
or filmmakers at that point
and you gave us access and trust
to document and tell your story
together with Billy Winner-Davis and Gary Davis
and your sister, Brittany Winner-Davis
and yeah, we are very, very thankful for that
and I really think that people take away from this film
not to be more scared
but to be inspired by the courage of reality
and her family as well
and really, you know, push back
against government suppression
so thank you very much, reality and Billy
and yeah, and I also, because, you know,
filmmaking is teamwork
and especially when you do independent documentaries
it's incredibly hard.
It's really, you were just asking the question
about, you know, the difference between
an investigative report and a documentary
and the difference is really
that an investigative documentary
has all these layers, you know,
you have to do the fundraising
to, yeah, to, you know, cover the travel expenses
and really be able to document a development
like this over years
and we felt so, you know,
we felt it was incredibly important
after I first, you know,
went to one of the first pre-trial hearings
to start filming and documenting
because there was so little media coverage.
I expected there would be, you know,
just camera crews outside and national reporters
and that, you know, everyone would cover this case
because not only was it, you know,
a national security whistleblower
and NSA whistleblower after Edward Snowden,
you know, disclose this information
about, you know, mass surveillance and data collection
but it was about election interference
and there was so much, you know,
it was such a contentious issue at that time
so I just expected that there would be such broad coverage
and when that didn't happen,
I, you know, I spoke to my producing partner,
you know, the day after I was at the pre-trial hearing
Ines Hofmann-Kena and I said to her, you know,
I thought there were many more journalists here
and it's not the case
and we just decided on the spot
that we have to witness it.
We have to pay witness, we have to document
because this was a historic case.
So Ines Hofmann-Kena, my producing partner,
she has, you know, produced all of my independent films
then the shoots that we did, the first one
and all the subsequent shoots were
with Torsten Lapp, who's over there,
can, you know, could you stand up for me
for a moment, director of photography,
person Lapp?
Torsten Lapp?
Torsten is, you know, we've worked together
for a very long time, over 15 years.
We started ARD's Panorama
and we filmed all of the independent documentaries
long and short together
and Torsten is someone who's never intimidated.
He is never deterred.
He, when you see these few rare images of reality,
you know, where she was, where they were just,
you know, taking her into the van and the car,
he was the one running behind the car and the van,
you know, just trying to capture an image of her
because they just, you know, they locked her away
and it was important for us to show who she is
and then we were sitting for two days
in a 100 degree seat in the car
trying to capture these rare images of reality in the jail
and yeah, Torsten is really someone who has a lot of courage
but also respect and compassion
and then Maxine Goetheke, the editor of this film
and all of my other independent films.
Maxine, could you please stand up as well?
So you might have seen this film
is a film that really shows the art
and the craft of an editor
and Maxine is an amazing storyteller.
She is a fantastic researcher who went through all
of the social media and, you know, really found
what I hope captures sort of the essence
of reality's humor and, you know, courage
and outspokenness and yeah, and also, you know,
throughout this journey really has so much compassion
and respect for the lead characters,
the protagonist whom she often meets, you know,
after the film is edited and laughs in Christ with them
and yeah, and really is so, you know,
has this, I don't know, the humanity to bring across
such a beautiful story that really goes through the heart,
I think, hopefully for all of you
and then in Zarudo of the composer
who also wrote the credit song
which is inspired by a reality winners poem
and then, you know, I also want to mention Marin Poitras,
not related to Laura Poitras
who was an associate producer
and who was also the actress in our recreations
so this was our very small independent team
who put together this film
and I couldn't do my work without them, so thank you.
Well, well done, you, all of you, thank you
and it does strike me that there's a number
of women involved in these projects
and there's, you know, looking at reality
and her mom seeing that as a dream team as well.
There's a lot of women talking about these issues
and working in the field of whistleblowing
and it strikes me that there is a real moment
of needing to consider how power is operating
and how it's working
and women do sometimes take the time to do that
and that may be part of what's going on, John.
I can just let you speak
but I do want you to,
well, I'm really interested in,
you said, well, we were listening to this,
just how many layers there are
and this is some of the nuancing
that just gets lost in whistleblower stories,
especially with this narrative of hero or traitor
and you just go down that road.
These are real people and they have real lives
and they are silly and funny and get on with things
and make mistakes just the same as the rest of us
and blowing the whistle
where you do get into hot water
with whether it's your employer directly
or the courts or the media affects the whole family.
So one of the things that comes through in this film
is it's a family project
but it also can have, it just does
and I know that that's a burden for many of the people
who have done these actions and they feel it
so I would love you to also mention a little bit about that.
Thanks for that.
There's so much to say.
I almost don't know where to begin.
I think I will begin by saying that the relationship
between Billy and reality is such a beautiful
and powerful thing and it's also very unusual.
You'd be surprised how often the government
will approach the spouse of a whistleblower
and say you're either with us or you're with them
because oftentimes we work in the same agencies, right?
Tonight is about reality
but I wanna tell one very short story.
My marriage didn't survive my whistleblowing
and I found myself involved in a custody dispute
which is not unusual and so I was in court recently
and my attorney asked me on the stand
was she a good wife?
And I said she was an amazing wife.
When I blew the whistle on the CIA's torture program
she went with me to the interview and sat just off camera
and when I finished I said how did I do?
She said you did great.
I said I didn't say anything classified, right?
And she said no, you did great.
And then her attorney called her up to the stand
and said is it true that you went with him
when he blew the whistle on the CIA's torture program?
And she said yes.
And her attorney said why did you do that?
And she said because the CIA's Office of Security
instructed me to go with him
and then to report back to them on his activities.
So to see these two together
and to see the love and the connection and the support
that's exactly the way that it's supposed to be.
That wasn't my experience.
Yeah, it was theirs.
I'm sorry to say that Tom Drake
and we're all such great friends
and in this very small whistleblower community
it's like we have a club.
We have dinner together
and one time I dragged FBI surveillance
to a dinner with Tom Drake
and he dragged FBI surveillance to the dinner with me.
And so we went out to go to our cars together
and he said which one is with you?
I said I think this one's with me.
I don't know this one, he must be with you.
And then they followed us home.
But anyway, that's the way the relationship
is supposed to be.
You know, we're all there for one another.
We're all there to support one another.
We're there to learn from previous whistleblowers
and the experiences that they had.
One of the things that I'm proudest of in my life
is that Ed Snowden told the New York Times
that Tom Drake and I inspired him
to go public with his revelations.
The same thing is gonna be said of reality winner.
One of the things that Ed said in the film
is so true and so powerful, it bears repeating.
Reality's sentence isn't gonna deter anybody.
No sentence is gonna deter anybody.
There was a wonderful study done
by an Israeli journalist named Al Press
about four whistleblowers in modern world history,
20th century whistleblowers.
And one of the things that he found,
one of the threads that he found
that ran through all of these cases
was that whistleblowers have an unusually
highly defined sense of right and wrong.
Much more highly defined than the general public.
And he also found that there is no such thing
as a deterrent.
You get a year, two years, five, 10 years in prison.
It doesn't matter because a whistleblower
can't sleep at night recognizing
that there's an injustice out there
about which he or she could do something.
I think reality would agree with me
when I say that on my very first day at the CIA,
I put my right hand in the air
and I promised to protect the Constitution
of the United States against all enemies,
foreign and domestic.
I hate to think that of the 300 people in the room that day,
I was the only one who actually meant it.
I know that reality meant it,
Tom Drake meant it, Ed Snowden meant it.
So whistleblowers are out there
and it's up to us to encourage them,
to help to protect them,
and God forbid that they're arrested to support them.
This film, frankly, was a giant leap in that direction.
Thank you, John, and we'll come back to you.
Billy, one of the things that I did want to ask you
and that sort of comes up a few times in your chapter
as well, which I did get a chance to read
and as you were talking in the documentary film,
there wasn't a lot of public support.
There wasn't a lot of media attention
to get that public support,
but we also heard elected officials and people in Congress
saying they wouldn't have known it
if they hadn't had the information
and that the substance of it was clearly important.
And at the same time, at the time
that they were relying on this information,
they were making it a point to say,
but we condemn whoever leaked it
and we don't agree with leaks.
And I'll come to John in a minute again,
but I just wanted to ask you a little bit more
about what was going on
and what are your theory's opinions about that,
about the lack of interest publicly
and then this need to say out loud
at the same time, thank God we know this.
Well, we shouldn't have known it this way,
but condemning the leaker.
Yeah, so I mean, that was one of the hardest things
throughout the last four years or so
was just trying to get support
and at least get support from any of our congressional leaders.
And we still to this day,
do not have the support of not one congressional leader.
And Sonya I know included in the film,
the piece where I think it was Claire McCaskill said
that she condemns the whistleblower,
but yet at the same time,
they were using the very information
that my daughter released to do their jobs
and they wouldn't have had access to it
had it not been released.
We had other reports where the states
that had been jeopardized did not even know
because nobody told them
until they found out about it through this leak.
And to me, I mean, that is just very telling
about the problems that we have
with our government in the United States.
When the government has gotten too big and too powerful
and they are keeping information from the American people
and you see it through reality's case
where the information when it gets out there
is so vital and so important and so useful
to all of these groups who are investigating this,
yet nobody will come to the defense
or support the person who actually gave them
the information because nobody wants to support.
I think that probably the charge of the Espionage Act
is something that played into that
because nobody wants to come to the defense
of somebody who's being accused of espionage.
And I think also in our country
that's something that needs to be worked on
is reform to get away from allowing our country
to use the Espionage Act against the people who release
the truth when we need it and people who blow the whistle
because that is something that I saw
that kept a lot of the support away from reality
because of that severe charge against her.
Do you think also the timing
because it was at the time that Trump had just been elected
do you think that there was some awareness
in terms of, I don't know, in the air
that if you were gonna say something and be critical
and agree that this information should have been out there
you wanted to sort of say out loud, just in case,
a little bit like I do believe in God
that I do condemn leakers
just so that that wasn't gonna be brought up against them.
Do you think there was something about the context
at the time that would be different now or not?
I don't think it's any different right now
because we're still not seeing any kind of support
for reality or other whistleblowers.
I was hopeful through Trump's administration
when leakers were just like a daily thing
and people were actually celebrating whistleblowers
and celebrating leakers
but yet that didn't stop our government
from persecuting them.
We saw other people who were charged
and who went to prison during this time
and again, no one in our Congress
will come to the aid or the support of a whistleblower
and actually support them.
John, you had Senator John McCain stand up on the floor
and say that the public owed you a debt of gratitude.
I was very fortunate.
Yeah, what's, where's the difference
or was it, yeah, if you wouldn't mind commenting.
I was, I don't wanna say I was fortunate
because that's really what it came down to.
After I blew the whistle and before I was arrested
I went to work for John Kerry
on the Senate Foreign Relations Committee staff
and Kerry's office in the Russell Senate Office building
was next door to McCain's office.
And so every time we would run into McCain in the hall
he would make a point, he would go out of his way
to come and shake my hand and say good morning,
good afternoon.
And I'd say good morning, Senator, nice to see you.
Finally, Kerry said to me,
why don't you two get a room or something?
And I said, no, it's the torture thing.
He's genuine.
He's really, he had reputation
for being the meanest man in Washington.
He was always nice to me, very nice.
And then when I got arrested, like Billy says,
official Washington goes completely silent.
Well, except for John McCain.
And when the Senate Torture Report finally came out
six weeks before I was released from prison
and proved that everything I said had been true,
McCain went to the floor of the Senate and gave a speech
and said that the country owed me a debt of gratitude
because if I hadn't gone public,
they would never, the American people would never have known
what their country was doing in their name.
And then he said privately
that he was gonna help me get my pension back.
Part of my sentence was that I lost my federal pension
and I had worked for 20 years in the federal government.
I had saved $770,000 in that pension.
I'm gonna have to work till the day I die.
I can't afford to ever retire.
And just weeks after he said,
I'm gonna help you get that pension back,
he got brain cancer and then died.
And that was it.
Nobody else on Capitol Hill
has ever said so much as good morning to me.
It's tough finding official support,
tough to impossible.
I wanted to come back to you, Sonia.
Yeah, there's a lot to take in.
You really did put it so succinctly
at the beginning of your talk
that you were in that courtroom
and there weren't other people there
that needed to be there to start reporting on this.
And do you have some theories about that
having then been with reality
and Billy for a long time after that?
I've been thinking about this a lot.
Why is there so little reporting on whistleblower stories?
I think in reality, winners case,
one of the reasons was also that it was not
in the Washington DC area
where you have a lot of national media
and especially national security reporters
and it is a little bit easier to get to.
I think that most of publications
or networks in the US really look at their bottom line
and the travel expenses
and especially in a pre-trial hearing like this,
you can't take cameras into the courtroom.
You don't get access to reality herself
and I think they might have thought
that they were not getting enough,
just standing outside the courtroom
and not having access, of course,
limits what people can report about
and I think they do that on purpose
and I also think they really worked very, very hard
to keep reality behind bars.
I actually never expected
that I would have to do another film
with an absent character,
an absent lead character protagonist
because I just thought at the beginning,
oh, she's going to be let out on bail
and we can have a conversation
and reality winner is going to tell her own story
and this just never happened
but I did not want to make this a reason
to not make a film
because it was even more important,
I failed to get her story out
when she wasn't able to speak for herself
and yeah, I think the other reason is too
that there is sort of this fear
of some major media organizations to lose access
to official press conferences.
I think there is pressure from the government
to not report on these type of national security
whistleblower stories
because they don't want to,
they might think and maybe you know more about it
but I could imagine that the government
is all about deterrence,
they don't want to incentivize anything
so they just don't want to have reporting about it
and yeah, so the corporate media,
afraid of losing access
and I think there's also an element of self-censorship
which I find extremely dangerous
where the general public but also reporters
are getting increasingly more scared and worried
about touching these type of stories
because they think, oh, maybe I can become a target,
maybe I shouldn't be asking this type of question,
I actually have heard,
even when I have been giving interviews,
I've heard journalists say to me before,
oh, after they asked me a question,
oh, maybe I shouldn't be asking this type of question,
I'm like, you're just asking a question.
Don't start self-censoring
and I think that is probably the most dangerous.
Yeah, it is affecting reporting around the world
and certainly some of what we were mentioning
just at the end of the documentary,
we're sitting beside each other about some of the fact
that the sentences are getting higher.
Before I move, I do want to come back to the Espionage Act
but I just wanted to ask reality,
if she might want to comment because I know,
I understand that you may not have seen the documentary
which is fine, you've had a lot to deal with
and just to return to be with your family.
You were, I think, released to home confinement in June,
is that right?
Have you been back with your mom since June
or have you only been back with her
and Gary since this week?
I've actually been on home confinement since June 9th
with an ankle monitor and constant phone calls
and threats of escape.
I ventured too far into my living room one day
and they told me I was escape status.
Just absolutely nerve-wracking
the way they could levy these threats
but they never documented.
So we had actually no accountability
or ways to address how we could prevent
the constant trauma from reoccurring
because then I would speak to the director
of the halfway house or my case manager
and they'd say, well, they never heard about it.
Meanwhile, I've had two panic attacks
and I'm physically ill from the stress
because they told me I would be charged with escape
the night before.
So yes, I have been home
but I haven't really been home.
It's been a constant sort of pressure on my family.
We've had back to back to back drug tests
every other week for five months
but I haven't had any approval to drive.
So that means, you know, mom or dad has to take me
to go get my drug test
and it's 100 miles round trip.
So it is a huge inconvenience
and you would think, okay, well,
the feds wanna test me and they wanna do it effectively.
Come to my house.
Come get a urine sample at my house.
It should be on them, but instead it fell to me
and the ankle monitor buzzed constantly
regardless of where I was, it never really worked.
I went grocery shopping twice in five months
because every time I got approval
they would suddenly pull approval
because for some reason if we were on home confinement
and they felt like COVID was getting bad
we were no longer allowed to go to restaurants
or go grocery shopping.
So I actually only went out to eat, I believe two
or three times in five months.
It just so happened COVID would tend to get bad
whenever we had family down for the weekend
and so they would belatedly tell me
that's why my social passes were disapproved the day of.
It was just a lot of coincidences like that.
So on Tuesday, this past Tuesday
I had my ankle monitor cut off
and I was released to go meet with my probation officer
and he tells me for the next three years
courtesy of my district in Georgia that sentenced me.
I have a 10 p.m. to 6 a.m. curfew,
365 days a year for the next three years.
That means no overnight trips no matter what.
No late night movies, nothing.
It also means I have to have special permission
to leave work earlier than 6 a.m.
I cannot leave the Southern District of Texas
but even if I could I would have to keep it
within a five hour drive so I can make it back in time
for that 10 p.m. curfew.
So they have without saying so directly
have effectively disabled me
from any type of meaningful travel.
That was a really crushing blow.
You know, I have a godson in Wisconsin
that I would like to go see.
My sister lives in North Carolina
and I just thought that maybe for the first time
in four and a half years I could bear
some of the burden for my family and go see them.
But now it's just being confined to this local area
for the next three years makes it really hard to feel how
how is this a step forward?
We have been using these same two clauses
from my plea agreement to sort of guide the way
to how I can speak to the media
and speak out on my own behalf
and finally advocate for myself and start over.
And on Tuesday somehow this probation officer's
interpretation even though the word interview
is not stated not one time in my court restrictions
for probation he just kept saying
well as long as you don't do interviews it'll be fine.
So I don't know what to do moving forward.
I don't know what the ramifications
of even a discussion like this will be.
So I'm happy to be here, I'm happy to be heard
but it just seemed like damn if I do, damn if I don't.
If I stay silent the abuse will continue
and if I speak out the abuse will continue.
Yeah, it's a really tough position to be in
and maybe I could ask John a bit about this espionage act
and how it operates but this seems a new twist.
That's unusually harsh and I wonder if it's
because it's Texas instead of one of the districts
in the DC area.
I don't know when I first got out of prison reality
I had a job offer at one of the oldest progressive
think tanks in Washington,
the Institute for Policy Studies.
And they wanted me to think the big thoughts
and write papers and talk about prison reform
and sentencing reform and things like that
and I accepted the position.
I sent it to my whatever they called themselves
case officers, whatever and they rejected it.
And I said, wait a minute, you told me
that if I don't get a job I'm gonna go back to prison.
So I got a job and you say I can't do it.
Why can't I do it?
And they said that it would be inappropriate
for me to comment on sentencing reform.
And I said, that's a violation
of my constitutional right to free speech.
I'm gonna accept the job and if you wanna send me
back to prison I'm sure CNN and others
would love to ask you plenty of questions, why?
And they backed off.
My experience with reporting to the halfway house
is the same as yours.
My halfway house was only seven miles away
as the crow flies but I wasn't allowed to drive
just like you.
So I had to walk a half an hour to the subway,
take the subway to Capitol Hill
and then get a bus that took another hour
to get to the halfway house which was in
the worst block in the worst neighborhood in Washington.
When I got off the bus one time a guy directly
across the street shot and killed another guy
and I jumped back onto the bus to protect myself,
the killer ran away and then I walked
to the halfway house to check in.
So I got a call one day saying get
to the halfway house immediately.
I said it's gonna take me two hours to get there
like it always does.
So I started the trek.
Two hours later I get to the halfway house
and they took me into the conference room.
It was the director of the halfway house,
the bureau of prisons representative
had driven in from Baltimore.
It was all this whole cast of characters.
And they said that they had decided
that they were gonna violate me
and send me back to prison
because I hadn't signed up for any
of the mandatory classes
and I had already been home for two weeks.
And I said your mandatory classes
are how to balance a checkbook,
which I know how to balance a checkbook.
How to write a resume, thank you very much,
but I don't need your help to write my resume.
And preventing suicide in prison.
I said isn't that like closing the barn door
after the animals already leave?
You should give the anti-suicide class
before people go to prison,
not when they get home and they're happy that they're home.
So I said, did you ever see that episode of The Simpsons?
When Homer Simpson is sentenced
to take a class on parenting
and he walks into the class a little bit late
and the teacher is saying,
put a garbage can lid on the garbage can people.
I can't stress that enough.
I said, is that what you're gonna teach me in your class?
To put a garbage can lid on the garbage can?
I said, I'm not taking your class.
And he says, step outside please.
And I said, and I want permission to drive.
I'm not gonna spend two hours getting here
and two hours getting back every single Tuesday
to take a stupid drug test.
You tell me I have to have a job
and then you take four hours out of my day.
I'm not doing this anymore.
I said, send me back to prison, I don't care.
I only have two months to go anyway.
So I went outside 45 minutes later, they came out
and they said, all right, you don't have to take the classes
and you can drive.
And I said, that's more like it.
And I left.
But I knew that they would back down.
In your case, I'm gonna email you
when I get back to the States on Sunday.
I have some ideas.
It sounds to me like they're picking on you
because they think they can get away with it.
And that's just wrong.
It's wrong, it's unfair.
And it's counterproductive, frankly.
Espionage Act.
Yep.
Yeah.
I have, as you might imagine,
I have a thing about the Espionage Act.
So the Espionage Act was written in 1917
to combat German saboteurs in World War I.
It was updated once in 1950
after the Rosenbergs had been executed.
This is the gravest crime
with which an American can be charged.
And it sometimes carries with it the death penalty, right?
Do you deserve the death penalty
when you expose waste, fraud, abuse,
illegality or threats to the public health
or public safety to the media?
Come on.
A precedent was set in the case of Tom Drake
in the district of Maryland
where the judge said that the government had to prove
that Tom Drake had criminal intent
that he intended to break the law
when he made his revelations.
He didn't have criminal intent
and the case utterly fell apart.
So when I went into court,
my lawyer said to the judge,
Your Honor, as per Judge Bennett
in the Tom Drake case, criminal intent,
Mr. Kiriakou had no criminal intent,
and the judge interrupted and she says,
I've chosen to not respect the precedent
that was set in the Tom Drake case.
And my lawyer said, Your Honor,
are you saying that a person
can accidentally commit espionage?
And she said, that's exactly what I'm saying.
And then she looked at me and she said,
Mr. Kiriakou, you either did it or you didn't do it,
and you did it, I knew I was finished.
And that was, I had only been arrested
a day or two earlier, three days earlier.
I was finished.
But this is the problem with the Espionage Act
and Ed Snowden will tell you exactly the same thing.
Ed Snowden has repeatedly volunteered
to return to the United States
and has told the Justice Department repeatedly
over the years that he is willing to go to prison
if he can stand up in court
and explain why he did what he did.
And they said, forget it.
You aren't gonna say anything in court.
And that's why he stuck where he is,
because they just will not let him
provide an affirmative defense,
or not even really an affirmative defense,
but an explanation that he did what he did
for the American people.
Now one thing about the prosecution
that's actually admirable if that's your bent,
is that they learn from each of our cases,
and they use that knowledge against the next whistleblower.
In the case of Daniel Hale, the drone whistleblower,
they raised reality's name in sentencing.
They raised my name.
I was there in the courtroom with Tom Drake,
and they said that in my case,
my sentence was far too short.
They realized after the fact
that they had agreed to a sentence that was far too short,
I had 30 months and I should have had 120 months.
And then because my sentence was so short,
then Jeffrey Sterling's was accidentally too short,
and then reality's was too short.
And the judge said, no, no, no, no, you don't.
That's not the way sentencing works.
And besides, reality winner was in Georgia.
We're talking about the Eastern District of Virginia,
and Daniel Hale ended up getting 45 months,
which is 45 months too long.
So there's a real problem with this SB&Age Act,
and the bigger problem is a political one, Anna.
Can you imagine somebody running for Congress
and saying, if elected, I'm going to make it harder
to charge people with SB&Age.
What district are you running in?
Nobody's gonna vote for that.
What you need is somebody with the courage to say,
look, this is the right thing to do.
This law's being abused.
It's being abused by the Justice Department.
The Justice Department needs to be reined in,
and we need to thank whistleblowers
who are willing to risk everything they have
to report on fraud, abuse, illegality, et cetera, et cetera.
The situation is flipped right now.
Yeah, yeah.
I know that we've covered a lot of ground.
I do wanna ask Sonya again,
and maybe this is something that reality
you would like to comment on, because it is about you,
and you mentioned it in talking about the editing
and the creativeness of reality.
And it comes out in reality,
your voice came out through your mom
and through the documentary and through yourself,
but as people talked about who you were,
I got a real sense of dedication,
incredible talent and intelligence like your sister,
my God, the three of you are quite the power,
three females of that family,
and I could see where you got some of this from your mom,
because although she doesn't call herself maybe an activist,
she's an advocate, and she's had to play
a really strange role of being a totally caring mom,
but angry as hell on your behalf,
has learned an awful lot about how to advocate,
who to talk to, how to work with media,
how to work with groups,
and Sonya was there watching her transformation,
maybe being a little bit a part of it,
and I wanted to talk about this side of reality
and maybe ask you reality first about your interest now,
and that side of you that is artistic.
I know you are very active and yoga
and run at marathons and weightlifting,
God, you lifted a weight in there
that scared the hell out of me,
but creativity really hits home,
and it hit home with the poem and the music at the end.
Is this something that just flows out of you naturally?
Is it something that you really think about
or it just is there?
I guess it's just there.
I kind of have these ADHD tendencies,
like lately I've been going out
into the scrap wood piles in the back
and trapping random things in resin,
that's kind of been my outlet,
lots of breaking glass with hammers,
just all the random stuff that you find yourself doing
when you're stuck at home,
but a lot of creating, using bits and pieces
from things I had created in prison
to kind of frame them in certain ways
to find some closure from all of that experience
and create pieces that express how I'm feeling now.
That sounds like an artist to me,
because just even thinking about resin,
I mean, when you said that I was like, of course,
I would never think of doing that,
but once you mentioned it, it makes so much sense
because there's beauty in that.
What did you, how did you find out about this side
of reality and how did you work to get this
as part of the documentary?
Because it's so strong.
Yeah, it is a big part and we realized,
Maxine and I, when we didn't get access to reality
and we knew this might not be the case
that we really wanted to make this film about her
and include her humor and her art and her words and poetry.
And it just, this is a selection in the film
of all these letters she was writing to her family
and supporters and people were just collecting them
and posting them on social media.
And then you go back and you see the diary entries
that are similar and also, so one of the reasons
was to really insert reality into the film.
But the second reason was because,
was that her social media, her diary entries,
but also her communication with her sister
became such a big part of the pre-trial hearings
and they were cherry picking all this information
that for me is one of the most important parts of the film
that I think should also resonate with the wide public,
honestly across the world because that is what can happen
when you have mass data, number one surveillance,
but also mass data collection and storage,
it's all there, the Facebook message conversation
that predates reality's arrest.
And I could tell in this audience
that this audience did understand reality's humor
better than the prosecutor.
But I remember in the courtroom or even when you saw
some of these TV clips that we were using
that people were taking it so seriously and out of context
and the prosecutor quoting one sentence
or one part of a diary entry.
And is this really the world we want to live in
where we have to censor our personal conversations
in a pandemic that's all digital with our friends
and families and loved ones or even our diary entries
that we think about what to put in our diary
and like in our diaries.
So this is where for me, reality's case
expands so much beyond whistleblowing
but also really is a case study on where things,
not are just headed but actually are at right now
where all this data is available and it doesn't have to be,
it doesn't have to be you but it can also be the people
who you love, your family members who all of a sudden
do something that speak out against something
that your government doesn't like
and then all your private conversations
are part of in this case a court case.
I'd like to turn to the audience
and see if we have some questions here
and I gather somebody's watching if there's questions online
and I have no idea how helpful I did about them
but are there any questions that people have
from the audience?
Because I know I can keep going
but I'd love to give you a chance.
Yes.
Is there a microphone running around?
My question's for reality winner
and I just wanna say thank you very much
for everything you've done for everybody in the world
and I find you extremely moving
and I'm born in 1985 so also on behalf
of our generation I say thank you very much
and those who are coming next
and also I would like to pre-curse my question
by saying I talk a lot in my private messages
with friends about murdering people
which I think I will now stop doing
but I have no intention to murder any of them.
Yes, yeah, just also to be clear
but I'm wondering my question isn't maybe not
it's not so much about the film
but I'd like to know about your pets
and what your pet status is now.
Did you hear that already?
So yes, I heard it, yes.
When it comes to animals our Facebook status is
it's complicated, we have four dogs, three cats
and a horse but the horse identifies as a dog.
That's why it's complicated.
He will run up on you, he barks at you,
we got him a nice bala hay
and he has destroyed it in less than a week
but the dogs are also extremely high maintenance.
They need certain dogs like to fight pretty bad
so they need to be kept separate
except when they're super sleepy
and then they wanna cuddle.
So you just never know, it's completely bipolar.
Now that I have a job in the local community
I am actually having like mom fears
about leaving them home alone
though I have like these contingency plans
of who goes where and if the weather is bad
who stays outside but who stays inside
and maybe we can rotate.
So yes, the four dogs are Domino, Daisy, Babyface
and Dobby, the house self.
The horse's name is Trouble
because he's nothing but Trouble
and then the cats are just irrelevant.
They pretty much self maintain
unless Fiona the princess likes to scream at us.
That is quite a crew you have at your house, Billy.
Are there other questions?
Say again.
I said the spiders are actually another situation.
There will be giant ones
like borderline tarantulas in the mailbox
but I'm not allowed to remove them
because my parents like to foster them.
Okay.
So that is the situation here as well.
Oh, it's snakes.
Yeah, I come from Canada.
I'm used to snakes.
Do you have snakes?
Yes, actually Sonya got to see our pet snake
and she was here visiting one time.
But these aren't pets.
These are animals that live around you.
Yeah, and sometimes come in and say hello.
Okay, great, great.
Are there other questions?
Yes.
First of all, thank you, reality
for your great courage here in Berlin.
The whole audience was frantic, impressed, moved
and I think also thank you, Billy
for encouraging your daughter
really super power mom.
And I think there was a big enthusiasm
at the end of the movie
and after hearing how you're treated now,
reality, I think we are all sobered.
And I think the atmosphere,
I had this impression changed a little bit
and we wish you all the best.
And so as I said,
after having watched this impressive documentary,
we had the impression that it's maybe over
but obviously we are naive
and I'm just trying to process
as we all, the irony.
And I think the irony goes around terms
like patriotism and shame and angst.
And I think there would be a whole world
to study about the reactions
of the US government right now,
actually under a Biden government,
which we maybe here in Berlin,
we would be so naive to think
that it would be all reverted to another angle.
And if you allow me to say from my background,
I don't know if it's of importance,
but I just cannot not mention it.
Next to art history, I studied Russian literature
and I was a lot busy
with the Soviet Union's oppressive system
and following and shame and patriotism
and being patronized and the whole psychosis
over condemned people,
not only in the 1920s century,
but maybe even currently.
So I think it's an irony of patriotism.
So I think there's a comparison possible to do
in this point, which is the biggest irony
when we look at the case,
when it's about Russia or the US.
So maybe there is a bigger theme going on
thinking about how a nation could defend patriotism
or should speak up.
So maybe at the end, maybe Sonya,
I would like after beyond thanking you
very much for this outstanding documentary,
would you plan to cover in the future the story
and help providing information?
And sorry, I spoke too long,
but I just wanted to get this out
and thank you so much, everyone.
Thank you.
Would you like to comment at all?
I'm not sure.
Like if I want to continue covering the story or...
Yeah, I guess that's good.
I'm definitely still following it.
And for independent filmmakers,
I think films do not end.
At least for me, they don't.
I'm actually still very close also to the lead characters,
the whistleblowers of National Bird,
the drone war documentary.
And I know we talked about Daniel Hale briefly earlier,
but he is still in prison.
And he did get a shorter sentence,
but he had also prior to the sentence
had many, many years of the sort of Damocles over him.
And that's the issue with the Espionage Act
that they were able to indict him
so many years after his raid.
And he didn't know when or if it would end.
And then the other thing why I'm so passionate
about bringing this information out about the Espionage Act
is that I have seen when I was investigating other cases
of not just whistleblowers, but also leakers,
is that they are not all treated the same under the law.
And that is what I as a journalist can really
comment on very strongly.
It's been applied very arbitrarily
and people like General Petraeus
have gotten away with a slap on the wrist and many others.
And that's what I know Billy feels very passionately
about as well, is that people are treated very differently
and there are different types of laws,
mishandling of classified information,
misuse of a government computer
that you could use instead of the Espionage Act,
but they do use the Espionage Act
particularly against national security whistleblowers.
I think that came out a lot in just some of your voice
in the documentary about this unknown
that you had to live with, the unknowns.
And even once you had had your plea deal arranged,
you were looking at, as you said, no strings attached.
I'm not sure if that felt better
to know sort of what the parameters were
or if it still felt like an unknown to you.
Is that sort of what you find the hardest
is just living with things
that you don't really have control over?
That is absolutely what this is,
is the parameters of my plea deal
are actually incredibly vague
and they don't actually list what the repercussions
are legally for even coming close to this line
that's like a mile thick.
You know, it's almost, like I said,
my probation officer is looking at the same conditions
that I've had legal scholars looking at for the past year
to prepare for this time
that I'm no longer in the department or the Bureau of Prisons.
And somehow he reads all these lines
and his summation is no interviews.
Does that mean I can't do an interview
about CrossFit?
I'm a CrossFit coach.
Why can't I talk about CrossFit?
Why can't I be a public spokesperson for rescue horses?
He doesn't seem to understand that.
But the ball is in his court
because there's no restrictions on what he can do to me
if he can remand me and to custody it at any point.
And because we can't seem to get my own country
to pay attention to what's happening to me.
Who knows how long it'll be before I can get released.
There's not gonna be any public support or public pressure
like in high profile cases.
Nobody's coming to help me out.
There's not gonna be any justice.
It'll just be being silenced all over again
and being alone and being in conditions
where I can't manage my mental illness anymore.
That's what I face every day
because they change the rules every day.
Billy, this sort of leads back to what you said
I think at the very beginning.
And it was something I think that seemed to hit you
that you needed to be your daughter's voice.
The first interviews that you were having,
Gary spoke and you spoke and you went inside.
You were trying not to be the main part of it.
You were upset and you wanted to talk about it.
But after a while, I think it was dawning on you
that you needed to be the person talking to the media.
And it brings me to that idea of your advocacy
and the public narrative.
Do you wanna talk a little bit about
how you go about changing that public narrative
or what's the value of it is in cases like realities?
Well, the value of what I've done these last four years
as far as being the spokesperson and speaking out
is to make sure that the system knows
that there are people out there who care
so that they can't abuse reality further.
My goal was to always make sure that there were eyes on her,
that there were eyes on the case and the situation.
And so that because if the system thinks
that nobody's watching,
that's when the system will abuse people.
You see it time and time again.
And so nothing, I know the Washington Post there,
big mantra is nothing good happens in silence or darkness.
And so that's kind of what I wanted to do
was make sure that there was not this darkness
around my daughter's case, there was not this silence.
And that since they did a really good job of silencing her
and also everyone involved in the legal case,
there was this protective order,
which in effect is a gag order.
Nobody could talk about it.
Somebody had to keep this case alive out there
on social media and in the media.
Somebody had to keep talking about it.
And that was what I felt like my role was
with the small group of supporters that I had
was to keep this alive.
Yeah, and Sonia, did you want to comment on that?
Because you by your seeing what needed to be done,
I think you've helped that go forward.
And I hope this is the beginning again,
a new beginning of keeping the light shone on this case
and on reality in Billy's lives.
Yeah, I just really hope anyone, the audience here
who felt moved by the film and reality winners case
especially the people who might have not heard
about reality winner before, just spread the word.
This is an independent film and production
and we really rely on word of mouth
to get it out there and share it as much as you can
with your networks because I do think that people
have to know about reality's story and also Billy's story.
I think that's a great time to stop, but I would...
Oh, there's a question from Tatiana.
We still have time, but yes, sorry.
Yes, I wanted to ask either to Billy or reality also,
who can and won't speak about the role of the intercept
because I think that was a really big point in the film
and also a big point in the story of reality.
Then in a sense, they burn the story
before it actually even came to the public.
And I think that this is a responsibility of the media
to protect the sources and also to make possible
that there is a story to speak about them
that then the press can refer to
and in the sense the person can be protected
because this become public opinion.
And for example, in the book,
I'm doing an interview with Laura Poitras
and she really speaks about that
and also the responsibility of the intercept
in actually burning the story before it came to the public.
And so I also wanted to know if you can comment on that
because I think we have also to openly discuss
about this kind of failure
because there was also a failure of the press.
And so I think it's really important that at the moment
to reflect on how the press can help you
and not really silence your case even further.
Do either of you reality or Billy want to make a comment?
Because I know John would have a lot to say.
I'll comment if you don't want to, but go ahead.
I would like to say that there's a very disturbing trend
and I know that journalists are aware of it
but in any sort of corporate media enterprise,
it becomes kind of corrupting in a way negative headline cell.
Negative headline cell, no matter what the facts are,
having a negative spin on it,
more so than a positive spin is far more lucrative.
And when a story isn't lucrative enough,
they find a way to make it more negative.
So in my case, it was a calculated move.
It wasn't a mistake.
They needed a martyr because it was more lucrative
and that's why they've repeatedly burned sources
because it's easier to champion someone
in a story that's overwhelmingly negative,
even if it's a manufactured sort of incident.
So they needed someone to have the fall
to make that information more lucrative
as a journalistic enterprise and corporate media.
And I paid the price.
And I wondered just as I was watching
if the fact that the story that the source
hadn't been protected also made the media
not really want to delve much into the story
because it was a story about a media failure
if they really were looking closely enough.
I can add a couple of things to intercept too.
Matthew Cole and Richard Esposito,
two of the journalists that were responsible
for essentially outing reality, also outed me.
I got an email one time from Matthew Cole
and it contained a dozen names.
And he said, hey, I'm writing a book about this rendition.
Can you introduce me to any of these 12 people?
And I responded, I don't know who these people are.
Kidnappings weren't my thing at the CIA.
I can't help you.
And he sent me a second email with another 12 names.
And I said, you clearly know this issue better than I do.
I don't know who any of these people are.
And he said in a third email, what about the guy
that you mentioned on page 100 and something
of your book, I think his name is John.
And I said, oh, you mean John Doe.
I said, I don't know whatever happened to him.
He's probably retired and living in Virginia somewhere.
I shouldn't have said the name.
I confirmed the last name that I'm calling Doe right now.
Well, Matthew Cole wasn't working for,
he wasn't doing this as a book.
There was no book.
It was a cover story.
It was a lie.
He was secretly working for the Guantanamo defense
attorneys.
So he had collected these 24 names.
I had confirmed the 25th and he sent all these names
to Guantanamo.
The attorneys there put the names into a classified motion
and asked the judge to demand that they be interviewed.
The judge realized that these names were all classified.
So he gave the names to the FBI.
The FBI went to the defense attorneys
and they said, where did you get the names?
They said from John Shipton, an investigator
for Human Rights Watch.
So they went to Shipton.
Where did you get the names?
From Matthew Cole.
So they went to Cole.
Where did you get the names?
Now, this is a journalist, mind you.
He said, I got him from John Kiriakou.
Then they convened a grand jury
and they called Matthew Cole.
Where did you get the names?
John Kiriakou gave me the name.
So they charged me with five felonies,
including three counts of espionage,
45 years in prison,
because Matthew Cole either was afraid,
feared for his own liability,
or he was working for the FBI,
which I've also come to believe is true.
Because it wasn't just me.
It wasn't just me and reality.
He did the same thing to an FBI whistleblower,
Terry Albury.
He outed Terry Albury to the FBI
and Terry Albury did three and a half years in prison.
You know, and they've done the same thing to Daniel Hale.
Blower.
Daniel Hale provided his information.
You know, the FBI's raiding his house
and he's getting four.
My brain can't process the notion
they are so stupid
or such bad journalists
that they keep making the same mistake
over and over and over.
I think reality's right.
They do it for the headlines,
but I'm more cynical
and I think they're working for the FBI.
I really do.
That's not a good, sorry.
There's a microphone issue.
If I could add something to that.
Sorry, Billy, did you want to jump in there?
I just also wanted to add throughout this,
I've always looked back at when the intercept
published the document that reality released.
They published it after her arrest.
They published it after her court hearing.
They had an agreement with the government
to hold off on the story until after her arrest.
When is it that a reputable journalist
or media source actually has an agreement
with the government on things like this?
Yeah, no, that sounds, there is a problem.
And I do think one of the things it raises,
whether there's a specific problem
with specific journalists and a specific organization,
there is a problem with, I think,
the self-censorship, the not wanting to touch the stories,
the issue of actually doing what you can.
Obviously, it is an arms race between investigative media
and some of these independent media
and the NSA and the whistleblowers.
And a lot of the power is we know where it sits.
And a lot of the idea that you're going to engage
in that battle and win is not easy.
So you need to, but the issue of journalism
and doing it well and doing it properly
has to be at the basis of whistleblowers
going to journalists.
And we can see that there are plenty of organizations
being set up outside of, and Intercept was one of them,
outside of the traditional media
to address some of these issues.
And right now, obviously, we also have the Espionage Act
being used against Julian Assange, a publisher,
and used transatlantically.
And the impact and the idea of how the Espionage
is going to, Espionage Act is going to continue
to affect journalists doing their jobs well
and properly in the public interest
is obviously not going to go away.
Sonia or John, would you?
May I add one thing to that?
There's a fantastic journalist and a friend of whistleblowers
by the name of, it's going to come to me in a second.
He's at BuzzFeed, Jason Leopold at BuzzFeed.
He's the king of the Freedom of Information Act.
In fact, a senior defense department official
called him a FOIA terrorist because he's uncovered
so much information about government wrongdoing
through the Freedom of Information Act
that they fear him now.
But anyway, he sent a Freedom of Information Act
request to the CIA about two years ago just on a lark.
And he asked for all communication between all journalists
and the CIA's Office of Public Affairs.
And they sent him thousands and thousands of pages
of just boring, useless, oh, I have a question.
What's the CIA director's birthday
and silly stuff like that?
But then he found a golden nugget.
Ken Delanian, the senior intelligence reporter
for NBC News and MSNBC, had been sending his articles
to the CIA for clearance before he sent them
to his own editors.
Why?
Why would he do something like that
if he's not putting CIA planted stories in the news?
It's because when you're a national security journalist
in Washington, it's a big deal to get invited
to the CIA Christmas party, right?
You get to shake the director's hand,
they'll let you go into the little souvenir store
and buy a CIA tie.
I'm serious.
And if you say something in your publication
or on your network that the CIA doesn't like,
you're not invited to the Christmas party next year.
And they're not gonna give you the little leak,
the little information that they want to plant
in the media.
And they're not gonna call you with a tip anymore.
They'll do all of those things
if you do exactly as they tell you to do.
And so that's what Ken Delanian was doing.
He was cowtowing to the CIA
to be on their good guys list.
Now part of the problem is that most publications
and networks in the United States no longer have a budget
for investigative journalism.
And so what they do is they take the CIA press releases
or they take the cleared paragraphs
that the CIA will send and they'll gist it
and they'll add a paragraph that they pull off Wikipedia
or wherever they find it.
And that becomes a news story.
But that's not news, that's propaganda.
We used to have a law in the United States
that forbade the propagandization of the American people.
What most Americans don't know is that that law
was revoked in 2011 as part
of the National Defense Authorization Act.
And so our news outlets now are legally permitted
to publish CIA and FBI propaganda.
There's nothing wrong with that anymore.
And either Americans don't know or they don't care.
I was just gonna throw a, you know,
oh, that's what called balance, right?
That's the giving each side there, say.
Would you, yeah, yes.
Would you like to comment on this issue?
Oh, yeah.
It's really very personal to me.
I mean, yeah, the funding, of course,
of investigative journalism is a problem
because it's expensive, it takes time.
You know, you saw at the beginning of the film
we are opening with a text card that says
that we were able to get the FBI interrogation audio
through a lawsuit, but against the FBI,
that was, you know, that started
with a Freedom of Information Act request.
Then after, you know, we have to give the FBI
quite a lot of time for them to react
because they put you on these like extremely long paths.
And then when nothing happened
and you know, we have to follow up
and they rejected it.
Then we went to the Department of Justice
and made our argument why we thought
we should get access to this material.
And then their DOJ quite surprisingly
actually sided with us.
It was sent back to the FBI and they still didn't move.
And at some point, you know, about one half years in
we went to the Reporters Committee for Freedom of the Press
and they provided pro bono support
because as an independent team, you know,
we cannot afford these type of legal expenses.
So they represented us and we sued the FBI
and it took almost two years, but we won.
And we actually had fortunately a judge
who sided with us when the FBI,
I think I was calculating, they said
it would take them 13 years or something
to release the data because they wanted to chop up
the audio into multiple smaller files
and release them every month,
which, you know, I know it takes a lot more time
than just releasing the file to us.
It already had been redacted.
So yeah, we got that, but it really,
it takes a lot of time and knowledge,
but I wish that big media organizations,
public media would really invest
in this type of investigative research
and not just, you know, a PR person, a press person
of an agency, that's not a source.
You know, if they give you information,
that is not, that's like a placing information.
That is not a source.
But I think you can actually find a lot of information,
like you mentioned with Jason Leopold,
through, you know, reading court records,
congressional budget reports.
I was reading through so many congressional budget reports
during the production of National Bird
and found a lot of information about, you know,
the drone program in these reports
and court records and so on.
And, but yes, it's dry work.
It doesn't, it's not as flashy
as having that, you know, new leak
that you have of classified materials.
So it's, you know, it really takes more time,
but I do, I really hope that the funding will be provided,
maybe by more foundations.
I mean, I saw here, this is supported
by every Van David Logan Foundation,
which actually has been a big sponsor of my work as well
and has made it able, possible for us
to do this long-term research.
But yeah, we need support.
We probably need more, you know, public support.
Maybe we have to go more to get funding from the people,
but it's important because there's a lot of information hidden
that is in the public interest.
And I think Reality Winner's Case
is one of the prime examples.
What could be more important to the public
than the security of our elections?
Thank you, Sonia.
I think that nicely brings us full circle
because I was thinking about Billy writing about We the People
and how your own belief in the American system
has been tested beyond, beyond what you could live with,
really, and that it's been destroyed.
But it does bring us back to We the People
because this event and everybody that's been involved in
publishing the book, putting this all together,
Reality, you taking that step to send that report.
And, you know, we thank you for that.
It does show where our accountability mechanisms are
failing.
You were trying to call that to account.
It's up to us to take on the rest of it with you,
but not leaving you to do it on your own
or Billy on her own.
So thank you so, so much for joining us today.
It really is an honor for us.
I don't know if you realize how much it has been
and it is, despite, I realize a difficult period
and it will take time and you will get more confident
about what's going on with your probation officer
and you'll hear from John.
But it is really important to know that you're not alone
and that we're out here trying to make this work better
for all of us.
So We the People, thank you.
Thank all of you.
Thank you.
I also wanted to thank really deeply Reality and Billy
for being with us this night.
I hope you are also going to follow us tomorrow
if you have time and you want to see how we go on here
in Berlin.
And I want to thank all the people in the panel,
John, Sonia and Anna.
This was really an important conversation.
And really, I would say,
we will keep thinking about your reality
and also I hope that this event will also help
in raising more interest and support for your case.
So we are with you and we stand with you.
I also then wanted to conclude the night of today
to remind you to come back tomorrow.
And briefly, I wanted to announce what is happening.
So we start at four with the book launch.
We're still blowing for change.
So I will be here together with Elena Velenoska
to speak more in depth about the work we did
together with other sort of people that wrote in the book.
And by the way, the book is here available
if you want and also online on EPUB and PDF for free
if you want to get it.
And then after that, we will have a panel
Crowdsourced Civic Action, subverting vigilance
and powering whistleblowers.
And together with me, there will be Barrett Brown,
Naomi Colvin, Lori Love and Mustafa Al Bassem.
And then we will have a second panel,
challenging discrimination and polarization,
whistleblowing the post-truth era,
together with Darryl Davies and Imashon Robert Trafford
of forensic architecture
and is moderated by Peter Matiasic.
I also want to remember
that there are two workshops on Sunday
that still have places if you want to attend.
One is building secure whistleblowing platform
with GlobalLeaks free software,
with Rimas Gair of GlobalLeaks.
And the other is two play or B-plades,
the gamification workshop with Agnese Trocchi
and Jacobo Anderlini.
The two workshop will be offline
and because of course it's also a matter of security
and small participation.
So I just remember again that you can just go online
and get your ticket there.
So this is it for today
and I really want to thank you again for being with us
and for this really important panel.
Thank you and goodbye to reality and Billy, see you, bye.